Good afternoon, everyone. Welcome to 213. It's good to see you.
Just a reminder that your attack lab is due tonight at 11.59 p.m.
You have one grace day for this lab, and CashLab will go out at right about the same time.
Now, it's going to be a little tight for Cash Lab. It'll be due next Thursday.
So you might want to get started on that soon.
Last lecture we learned about the memory hierarchy and the idea of caching.
Today we're going to look at a very important kind of cache, which are called cache memories.
And they're very important to you as a programmer because they can have such a big impact on the performance of your program.
So if you know about the existence of these cache memories and you know how they work,
as a programmer, you'll be able to take advantage of that in your programs.
So last time we looked at the memory hierarchy is a collection of storage devices
with smaller, costlier devices and faster devices at the top and faster devices at the top and slower, cheaper, cheaper, much
larger devices at the bottom.
And then at each level in this hierarchy, the device at level K serves as a cache holds a subset of level K
serves as a cache holds a subset of the blocks of the blocks that are contained in the device at the lower
level K plus 1.
Now recall the general idea of caching, so we have a memory, it's an array of bytes, and it's an
of bytes and we break it up arbitrarily into a collection of blocks.
And this memory is larger, slower, and cheaper, and so it's much larger than a cache, than a cache,
which is smaller, faster, and more expensive, and which holds a subset of the blocks that are contained
in the main memory.
And then blocks are copied back and forth between the cache and the memory in these block-sized transfer
units.
So for example, if our program requests a word that's contained in block number 4, it asks the
cache to return the word that's contained in block 4.
The cache looks and it's at the blocks that it's, the subset of the blocks that it's stored, discovers
that block 4 is not there, so it asks the main memory to send it block 4, which it does in a, and
And then when that block arrives at the cache, the cache stores it potentially overriding
some existing block.
Similarly, if our program asks for a data word that's contained within block 10, the cache looks,
sees that it doesn't have that block.
So it requests that block for memory, which copies it into the cache, which overrides
a data word that's an existing block.
Now subsequently, if our program asks for
a request or if our program references a word that's contained in block 10,
for example, then the cache, then we have a hit and the cache can return that block immediately without
going through the expensive operation of contacting memory and fetching that block from memory.
Now there's a very important class of caches, these so-called cache memories
which are contained in the CPU chip itself and are managed completely by
hardware and they're implemented using fast S-RAM memories.
And the idea for this cache, which is right next to the register file, is to hold frequently access blocks or blocks
or blocks from main memory that are accessed frequently.
Okay, so hopefully, because of the principle of locality, most of our requests for data
will actually be served out of this cache memory in a few cycles rather than
in this that rather than from this slow main memory.
Now cache memories are managed completely in hardware.
So this means that the heart, there's, there has to be hardware logic that knows how to look for blocks in the cache
cache and determine whether or not a particular block is contained there.
So cache memories are, have to be organized in a very kind of strict,
simple way so that the logic, the lookup logic can be pretty simple.
So this is very, um,
All cache memories are organized in the following way.
You can think of the, you can think of the cache as an array of S equals 2 to the S sets.
Okay.
Each set consists of E to the 2E lines, where each line consists of a block of B equals 2 to the B bytes of data,
a valid bit, which indicates
whether these data bits are actually, the bits in the data block are actually meaningful,
right?
It's possible they could just be random bits.
Like, you know, when you first turn on the machine, there's nothing in the cache,
but those bits will have values, right?
That they'll either be ones or zeros, but they won't actually correspond to data.
Okay, so the valid bit tells us if these B-bytes actually mean anything.
And then there's some additional bits called the tag bits, which will help us
search for blocks, which I'll show you in a minute.
Now, when we talk about our cache size, we're referring to the number of
of data bytes that are contained in blocks.
And so each cache has, there's S sets, there's E blocks per set, and there's B bytes per block.
Okay, so the total cache size C is S times E times B times B.
Okay.
There's a lot of terms to sort of keep straight, and it's very easy to get, to confuse the difference between lines and blocks and lines and sets.
Okay, so we'll go through some examples, and hopefully these will start to make more sense.
Now let's look at, in general, how we, how the cache hardware implements a read.
So when our program accesses, when our program executes an instruction that references,
references some word in memory, the CPU sends that address to the cache and asks,
and it asks the cache to return the word, the word at that address. So the cache takes that address.
And so the cache takes that address, this would be a 64-bit address in case of x86-66-64.
And it, it divides the address into a number of
a number of regions which are determined by the organization of the cache.
Okay, they're determined by those parameters.
S sets, S, the number of sets, E, the number of lines per set, and B, the size of each data block.
So the low order bits, there are B, low order bits, which determine the offset in the block that that word starts at.
The next S-bits are treated as an unsigned integer, which serves as an index into the array of sets.
Okay, remember, we just think of these as, think of this cache as an array of sets.
The set index bits provide the index into this array of sets.
And then all of the remaining bits, all of the remaining T-bits constitute, uh, constitute what we call a tag.
what we call a tag, which will help us when we do our search.
So the cache logic takes this address and it first extracts the set index and uses that to, as an
index into this array to identify the set that if this block is in the set, I'm sorry, if the
data word, if the block that contains the data word at this address is in the cache, it's going to be in the
set denoted by the set index.
Okay.
So first it identifies which index to look in, and then it checks the tag, it checks all of the lines in that
checks all of the lines in that set to see if there's any, any of those lines have a matching tag, that
a tag that matches the T, the tag bits in the address.
Okay.
And if, and it checks to see if the valid bit is turned on.
So if those two conditions holds, if there's a line anywhere in the set,
as of where the valid bit is one and there's a matching tag, then we have a hit.
Okay, then the block that we're looking for is contained in this set.
Okay, if we, once we determine that, that we've identified the block, then the cache uses the
low order B bits to determine where that, where the data we're interested in begins within
that block.
All right, let's look at a more specific example for a, a, uh, a, a, a,
the simplest kind of cache, which is when E equals one, when there's only one line per set.
Okay, so E equal one, one line per set.
This kind of cache is called a direct map cache.
So here we have S sets. Each set consists of a single line.
And now suppose our program references a data item at a particular address.
The CPU sends that address to the cache. The cache takes that address, breaks it up into
these three fields and for this particular address, the block offset is four,
and the set index is one, and then there's some tag bits, which we'll just denote with, which
will just denote with, as a color pink.
So the cache extracts the set index, which is one, and then it uses that as the index into the set.
And then it can just, it just ignores all the other the sets.
If the block we're looking for is in the cache, it's going to be in this in set number one.
Then it does the comparison of the tag bits and the valid bits, and assume that they, assume that valid bits on and that it matches.
Then it looks at the block offset, which is four, and which tells it that the four byte end, suppose that that's what the instruction was referencing, the four byte in begins at offset four.
So now the cache takes,
this and it sends it back to the CPU which puts it in the register.
Okay, if the tag doesn't match, then the old line, if the tag doesn't match, then there's a miss.
And in that case, the cache has to fetch the block, the corresponding block from memory,
and then overwrite this block in the line.
And then it can serve, then it can fetch, it can get the word out of, out of the block and send it back to the processor.
Let me ask you a question just to see if, kind of check to see if you're following along with this.
So if there's a miss, and the cache has to request the block from memory, fetch it from memory,
and then overwrite the block in the current line.
Does it also have to change the tag bits, or do those stay the same?
So do the tag bits that were in this line get overwritten with a different value?
or is it the same?
Same?
Different.
Now why would it be different?
We haven't changed?
Yes.
I'm sorry?
Oh, it almost certainly has different data.
But does it have a different address?
Exactly.
It missed because the tag,
it missed because the tag didn't match.
If the valid bit was false and the tag matched,
then that would also be.
Oh, then you wouldn't.
Okay, that's right.
Okay, good, good, good.
Okay, great.
Let me do a little, let me do a really simple,
specific example of how direct map cache works.
I want you to understand in real detail how this would work,
but I also want to make a point about
the weakness of direct map caches
and why you would want to have more than one line per set.
one line per set.
Okay, so we, this is a really simple,
we have, our memory system consists of 16 bytes.
Okay, so it's not a very useful system, with four-bit addresses,
and it's broken up into blocks of two bytes each.
Our cache consists of four sets with one block per set.
Now, our four-bit addresses, because B equal 2, that's 2 to the 1,
two to the one, we only one block offset bit, right?
There's only two bytes in a block, so the byte we're looking for is either at zero or one.
Okay.
Because we have four sets, we need two set index bits, and then the remaining bits are always
tag bits, so in this case there's just one tag bit.
All right, now let's suppose that our program
executes instructions that reference the
the following memory addresses, 0, 1, 7, 8, and 0.
And these references are reads that they're reading one byte per read.
Okay, like I said, this is a really simple system.
So let's look at what happens now.
We start out, our, our, our, our, our cache is empty,
valid bits are all set to zero, and now the cache receives a request
for the byte that's at address zero.
So it extracts the cache,
the set index bits, which in this case are zero zero.
So these, so it's going to look in set zero for, and in this case, since valid is zero, it's just, it's
a miss, okay?
So it fetches that block from memory, sticks the block, so this memory, this is the, this is
using array notation for memory, so this is like the, the bytes that extend from offset zero to
offset one, inclusive.
in memory. The tag bit is zero and a valid bit is one. Okay, now the next address
address that comes by is for address 1. Well, that's a hit, right? Because we've, that block,
the block that contains, the byte at address 1, is already in the cache. The tag and the tags match.
Okay, so we're good. That's a hit. Now we get address 7. So the cache extracts the set index bits, which in this
case are 1-1, or 4, or 3, or 3, looks in set 3, there's no valid bit, so that's
a miss, and it loads the data from memory that spans bytes 6 and 7.
In this case, the tag bit is 0, okay, so we record that, we record that in our metadata.
Okay, the next reference that comes by is 8.
Now 8 has a set index of 0, 0-0.
But that's currently occupied by block 01.
And we can tell that because address 8 has a tag of 1 and the existing block, the
the block at the earlier address at address 0 has a tag of 0.
So that's a miss.
So now we have to go fetch the block containing byte number 8 into memory.
So now we have bytes 8 and 9.
and our new tag bit.
Okay, now the next instruction is for byte 0, and we just, we just replaced, we had that in, we had that in our cache, and we just replaced it.
So, so it's another miss.
So that's unfortunate.
And it's the only reason we missed it is because we've got just one line per set.
Right, so we were forced to overwrite.
that block containing bytes, the block 01,
when we, when we missed on block 8,9.
Okay, so this, and you see there's plenty of room in our cache.
We've still got, we've got two, two lines that we haven't even accessed.
Right? So we've, our cache is plenty big,
but just because of the sort of the low associativity of our cash
and the sort of the pattern, the access pattern,
that we were presented with, we've got a miss that really seemed it was kind of unnecessary.
So, oh yes, sorry.
So when we referenced, when we referenced seven, it's actually the, it's at offset one in that block,
six, seven.
Okay, since our blocks are two bytes, they'll always start on an even multiple.
Any other questions?
Okay, so this, so this sort of, is the reason why you have cash
have higher associativity, higher values of E.
So let's look at, and so for values of E greater,
for values of E greater than, greater than one,
we refer to them as E-way set associative caches.
So here, E equals two, so it's a two-way, it's two-way associative.
So let's suppose we have a two-way associative cache.
So here we have our array of caches.
We have our array of sets.
And now each set contains two lines, okay, instead of one line.
And suppose we're presented with an address with the following form.
We're looking for a word that begins at an offset of four inside our block at within set number one.
Okay, so the cache extracts that's set index.
So this is set zero.
This is set one, this is set two, throws away all the other sets.
And now in parallel, it searches, it searches the tags, it searches for a matching tag in both of these, both of these lines, and and a valid bit.
So if we get a matching tag and a valid bit true, then we've got a, then we've got a hit.
Now that, yes.
Yes.
Oh, it's a very good question.
So there's hardware logic that does that compare.
And that's the reason that as the number of, as the associativity goes up, that logic gets more and more expensive.
Okay, it's like some, like you're kind of doing some kind of tree search.
And so that actually is the limit.
That's why, I mean, because in general, right, the, if you take this to the limit, there's just one set with, there's just, it's, we call that
a fully associative cache. So there's just one set, and now any block, a block can go anywhere,
right? There's no constraints now and where you place a block. But the, because of the complexity of that,
that fully associative search, those are very rare. In fact, we do see, we'll see, fully
associative caches, but there's software caches. So in software, so in software, so the complexity of the, the
complexity of the hardware and sort of doesn't, doesn't, doesn't, doesn't, it's not worth, it's not worth the complexity of the hardware for the penalty of having a lower associativity.
Okay, but there are some systems, later on when we study virtual memory, the, in a virtual memory system, the DRAM serves as a cache for data stored on the disk, and as we saw you last time, the penalty for a miss, if you have a cache,
if you have a cache on DRAM and you miss, and you have to go to disk, the penalty is huge for that.
And so because of that, it's worth, it's worthwhile having very complex searches, search algorithms,
and in particular, in a virtual memory system, that the DRAM is, implements a fully associative cache, where blocks from disk can go anywhere.
We'll get into that later when we look in virtual memory.
But you're right, you'll see in real systems nowadays that the number goes up, right, because
features are going down and designers can afford to implement more expensive hardware.
But the largest associativity on Intel systems that I know of is 16-way associative L3 caches.
And then the others are 8-way associative. So that's sort of the order of magnitude that's state-of-the-art
right now. Okay, so then once we've identified a match, we use the set offset bits.
In this case, we're accessing a short inch. So four is the offset within the block.
of this, the two-byte short end, which then we can return to the processor.
All right, so let's do that same simulation that we did before, but this time, with a two-way associative cache.
Now, memory system is the same, but now instead of one set, we have two sets.
And, I mean, I'm sorry, instead of four sets, we have two sets.
So the cache, this is the same-sized cache, but we're just going to organize it differently.
Instead of one way, instead of a direct map cache with four lines, containing four lines,
one line per set, we're going to implement a two-way associative cache where we have two sets with two lines per set.
Okay, so in each case there's just four, there's four total lines.
Question?
Oh, so that comes in with the request somehow.
And I actually don't know the details of that.
It may, I guess there's so, it could ask for just, there could just be a default size, maybe a default size, maybe a
it's always a 64 byte word and then the processor extracts the current bits.
I actually don't know the details of that, but it either comes in on the request or there's a standard,
there's a standard size that the processor then parses out.
We'll just assume that the cache knows what size to return.
Yes.
How do you decide which block to replace?
That's a really good question.
So there's a lot of different algorithms.
The most common algorithm or a common algorithm is least recently used.
So by locality, you want to keep blocks in the cache that are being used a lot.
And so if a block isn't referenced for a long time, by the principle of locality, by sort of the
inverse locality principle, it's likely not to be addressed referenced in the near future.
So that's one, that's one algorithm that you just keep track.
of and I'm not showing there there needs to be additional bits in the line
to sort of keep like sort of virtual time stamps that but that's that's that's a that's
sort of the general way you do it just try to keep the things that are the blocks that are
being accessed the most frequently the most recently yes okay the question is what
determines the block size that's determined by the design of the memory system so
that's a that's a fixed parameter
of the memory system. So when the Intel designers decided to put cache memories
on their processors, they decided that the block size would be 64 bytes. Sorry?
So the block size comes, the block size comes first. Then, then you determine how big
you want your cash to be. Okay? And then, and you determine the associativity. Okay, and then once
you've determined the associativity and you know how big your cache is, then that
that determines the number of sets. Okay. So basically all of those, uh, the, the, the, the number
of lines and the capacity, the number of lines per set is sort of a fixed high-level parameter,
design parameter. The size of the cache is a, is a, is a, is a high-level design
parameter, and then the number of sets then is induced from that.
Yes.
Ah, that's, yeah, how does, so that's, so that's, that's, that's, that's the replacement policy.
How does it, so the question is, how does it, how does it, when there's multiple lines in a set, how does it determine which to over, overwrite?
And that was what, that was the previous question, probably, maybe I should have repeated it.
So you, you, you try to pick a line that, that was least recently used.
So lines, lines that haven't been accessed recently are good candidates for replacement because, because of the sort of the sort of
inverse locality principle, right?
That they haven't been inverse referenced recently, chances are they won't be referenced.
Again, oh, yeah, there's additional bits that I'm not showing here that you have to.
So, so when you replace a line in the set, if that data has changed, then it has to be written back
to memory. And that's another bit I haven't shown. Yes.
Ah. So the, so, yeah, so this is a really, this is a really tricky parameter, right? And it's a, it's a
high-level system parameter that's that goes on for years. So the idea, you want to have
blocks in order to exploit spatial locality. Right, think about it. If you're going to go to the trouble
of, if you have a miss in cash, and you're going to go to the trouble of going all the way to memory
to get some data, you want to, you want to amortize the cost of fetching that data by
fetching more than one bite. That's the motivation for blocks. Because by, by, you want to,
By the principle of locality and spatial locality in particular, if you reference a word inside of a block, chances are you're going to reference a nearby word, which will also be in that block.
Okay, so blocks, the whole purpose of blocks is to exploit spatial locality.
Now, if you make your block too small, then you don't amortize, you don't get the same amortization, right?
You maybe get one, you bring the block in.
So there's a reference. You get a miss. You bring the block in. There's another reference nearby. You get a hit because the blocks in memory. But then the next reference is in a different block because your block sizes are too small. So you kind of want to make blocks big as big as
but without slowing the system down. So if you made your block size too big, it would just take too long to bring that block in.
Plus, plus now your blocks are taking up bits in your cache memory.
So now there's no room for other blocks, right?
So it's a really, it's a really tricky design problem, right?
And I, if we're taking an architecture class, then we would sort of dive into the, you know, how architects make those design decisions.
But in general, that's what they're, it's kind of a balancing act, right?
Were there any other questions?
Yes.
Oh, the question is every time there's a miss, do you have to, do you have to select a victim line and overwrite it?
Yeah, I don't know of any.
that don't do that. Now we'll see when we look at rights, we'll see there's an option of whether
we're only looking at reads right now. But with rights, that question does come up. And if you
wait in a couple of slides, we'll go over, we'll go over that. Any other questions? Okay, so let's
look at this two-way associative cache now. There's, there's one block offset bit. We only have two
so that we only need one set index.
And then the remaining two bits are tagged.
So let's go through our trace.
So address zero has a set, is in set zero, right here.
That's a miss.
So we load that into memory.
The reference to address one, that's in set zero, and that's a hit because that bite is in our block.
The reference to seven is a miss, that's in set one.
So we load that.
And we were just picking, randomly pick, one of these two overwrite because the cache is empty.
The next reference is to address number eight, which is in set zero.
Now here's the difference between the direct map cache and this two-way set associative cache.
When we reference address eight, that block has to, the corresponding block has to go into set zero because of this zero set-inset.
index bit, but we've got room now because our sets have room for two lines instead of one.
So when we load that in, if we have an available empty slot, we'll put it there, we won't overwrite anything, right?
So if possible, we'll always try to overwrite empty, empty lines.
So now we've got, in this set, we've got block 01 and block 8, 9.
So when we get our reference to block to address zero, whereas before with the, when we have
a conflict miss in the direct map cache, now we can satisfy that request.
It hits a memory and the cache can satisfy it from the cache instead of going to memory.
Okay, so that makes sense? Okay, now what about rights? So there's multiple copies of
the data, right? We're subsetting, as we move up the hierarchy, we're creating subsets of the data in
the caches. So what do we do if we do a write to do a write?
to a word within a block that's currently in the cache.
Okay, we have two options.
We can write that block immediately to memory, right?
We've got a block that's like this big and we're updating a little chunk of it.
So we can either do the update and then flush it to memory immediately so that memory always mirrors,
the contents of memory always mirror the contents of the contents of the cache.
Okay.
But that's expensive, right?
I mean, you know, memory accesses are expensive.
So the other option is what's called write back.
So in this case, when we write to a block in the cache, we don't flush it to memory until we elect that particular line as a victim that's going to be overwritten.
And only then, only then when we're just, we sort of defer the writing to memory until the last possible minute,
we defer it until just before.
just before the cache would overwrite that data block.
Okay, so that's called write back. And for write back, you need to have some, an extra bit in the line
that indicates whether that block's been written to. So the algorithm is when the cache
cache identifies a particular line to overwrite, it checks the dirty bit on that line. If it's set,
then it writes that data to back to disk. Okay. If the, if the data hasn't, if that block
It hasn't been written, there's no point, there's no need to write it back because it's the same, it has the same value as the copy of the block on disk.
Okay, now, so what about, so that's a right hit?
Now, what happens if we have a right miss?
So we're doing a right to memory, and the word that we're writing is not contained in any block that's in our cache.
Okay?
So we have two options.
We can do what's called write allocate, so we can treat it if there's a miss, we can do sort of the
thing that we did with a hit, which was create a new, a new line, possibly overwriting an existing line.
And then write in, so we could, so we could create that cache entry, that cache line, fetch it from memory, and then do the, do the right.
Okay. So this is sort of symmetric to reads, right? So every right, if it misses, when the
right finishes, that block will be in the cache. And if we do a subsequent read,
we get a hit.
Okay, so that's the reason you might want to do that.
The other option is just to, don't allocate an entry in the cache, don't allocate a, an entry in the cache,
don't allocate a new line, just write the data directly to memory.
You don't really need to understand the distinction between these two things.
Different caches use different policies.
For your own mental model, a good model to use is just to assume right-back, allocate.
So just assume that we won't copy the data to disk.
If there's a hit, we won't write it back to disk until the last possible minute.
And every time there's a right miss, we'll create a new entry in the cache.
Okay, so that's, I think that's sort of the simplest model that, and it's a reasonable model that you can use,
regardless of the particular cache implementation.
Now, in a real system, so far we've only looked at, we've only assumed that there's a single cache,
cache, but in real systems, there's multiple, multiple caches.
So modern core I7 has well architecture from Intel, contains multiple processor cores.
So four is a typical number for like desktop systems.
Eight, eight to twelve is typical for server class systems.
These processor cores can each execute their own independent and system.
independent instruction stream in parallel.
And each processor core contains general purpose registers, which that's level zero in the cache.
And then two different kinds of L1 caches.
The data cache, the L1D cache, and the I cache, which is the instruction cache.
And these are fairly small, 32K bytes, they're eight-way associative, and they can be accessed,
can be accessed in a very small number of cycles.
The next level of the hierarchy is an L2 cache, which is still fairly small, 256K bytes, same associativeity,
and it has a slightly longer access time.
And it's unified in the sense that the L2 cache contains both data and instructions.
Okay.
So that's all within a single core.
on the chip.
And then also on the chip, but external to all the cores and shared by all the cores, is an L3 unified cache,
which is 8 megabytes and 16-way associative with an access time that's like 40 to 75 cycles.
So if there's a miss in L1, then the L1 sends a request to L2 to try to find the data
in L2.
Since L2 is a little bigger, maybe maybe the data.
hasn't been flushed out of L2 yet.
If L2 can't find it, it sends a request to L3 to see if it can find the data in L3.
If L3 can't find it, then it gives up and it goes off chip to memory.
Yes, question.
Yes.
Main memories is, that's the DRAM built of DRAM chips.
It's separate, it's in a separate, separate set of chips on the motherboard, connected by those, that IO bridge
that we and the bus, various buses that we talked about last time.
And for all different, for all of these different caches, the block size is 64 bytes.
Now, there's a number of different ways to think about the performance of caches.
My most common way is using a metric called the miss rate.
So what, this is the fraction of references that miss.
So we're very, so if, and it's, it's one minus the hit.
hit rate. So typical, for caches to work, the miss rate has to be pretty low.
And fortunately, because of locality, these misrates are low.
Another metric is the hit time. So if we do have a hit in the cache, how long does it actually
take to sort of look up the, you know, do the look up to determine that there was a hit and then
return the value? So for L1 and an intel system, this is 4 o'clock.
cycles, 10 clock cycles for L2. And then there's an additional cost if, so
you always have to pay the hit time, right? The hit time is the best you can do. But if you have a miss,
then it's, you pay the hit time because you have to do the search and eventually you're going to have
to return the word back to the requester. But then you have this additional cost which you have to go,
which is going to the memory to fetch the data. Okay. So that, that mispemble
That's so-called mispenalty is on the order of hundreds of cycles for main memory.
But at other levels of the hierarchy, it can be huge.
So the miss penalty, if you have a cache in main memory, that's caching blocks that are stored on disk,
the miss penalty is enormous.
So it's kind of interesting, if you think about it, that performance is, the performance of these systems is very sensitive to the misrate, much more sensitive than you would think.
sensitive than you would think. And in fact, 99% hit rate is twice as good as a 97% hit rate.
Yes. Yes. Yeah, the hit. So the question is, does the hit time include the time to access the tag?
And yes. So the hit time is the time it takes you to search to determine if that item is in the cash and then return it.
Yeah, so the, yeah, so the, the, the miss penalty is the time it takes for the cache to fetch the data from memory.
So that's all the latency, you know, going across the buses, the time it takes the memory to respond to the request, the time it takes the data to flow back over the buses back to the cache.
So the time for a miss is going to be the hit time plus the miss penalty.
So, I mean, imagine
Suppose there's a hit time of one cycle and a miss penalty of 100 cycles, those are reasonable numbers.
So the average access time, if you have 97% hits, it's the hit time plus the percentage of misses times the miss penalty.
So that's four cycles for the average access time. But if we just increase the hit rate by 2%, the average access time drops by 50%, a factor of 2%.
All right. So why, why is this stuff important? Why should you care about it?
So caches that we, as we've seen, are these, these, they're automatic, they're all built-in hardware.
There's no part of the, sort of the, sort of the visible instruction set that lets you manipulate caches and your assembly
machine code and programs.
So it all happens behind the scenes automatically in hardware.
But if you know how, if you know about the existence of caches and you have this general idea of how you can work, how they work,
then you can write code that's cash-friendly in the sense that your code will have a higher, higher
misrate than code that that isn't cash friendly. So the idea is to, you want to focus on making the common case go fast. Don't spend your time on code that sort of code that doesn't get executed very much. So look at the most commonly called functions. And then within those functions, look at the inner loops of those functions. Because it's the inner loops that are executing the most, right? So you can, as a first approximation, you can just ignore sort of stuff. If you have
nested loops, you can ignore stuff that's going on in the outer loops.
And just focus on the code in the inner loop.
Now what you want to do is try to minimize the misses in the inner loop.
Okay, so repeated references to a variable is variables are good, especially if those are
local variables. Right? So remember, if you declare a local variable in C, the compiler can put that in a register.
Right? If you're referencing global variables, maybe not. The compiler doesn't
know what's going on. So it can't put that reference to that variable in a C in a register.
Okay, so repeated references to local variables stored on the stack are good because those will get turned
into register accesses. You'll never go to memory. Okay, also stride 1 accesses to arrays are good.
And they're good because of the existence of these blocks, right? So the only way you'd know that
that stride 1 references are good is if you knew that caches have these
64-byte blocks.
Okay, so the, and stride 1 reference will have half the miss rate as a stride 2 reference.
Because if you're doing stride 1 references, the first reference to a word and a block will miss,
but then subsequent references will hit.
And you'll hit, if you're doing a stride 1 reference, you're going to hit every word in that block.
If you're doing stride 2 references, you're only going to hit every other word.
So you'll only get, you'll get sort of half the, so you'll miss at twice the rate.
So basically the point I want to make to you is that our understanding of caches allow us to sort of quantify this,
this qualitative notion of locality that we developed the last time, right?
The last time we looked at, we said if it's doing stride 1 references, that's good.
if it's if we're doing, if we're accessing the same variable over and over, that's good.
But if we understand caches, now we can quantify it in terms of misrate.
All right, so let's finish up.
The rest of the class, we're going to look at the performance impact of caches on your code.
Okay, and why, why you need to know about these things and that the impact that they can have.
So there's a very interesting function that's actually plotted on the cover.
actually plotted on the cover of your textbook that we call the memory mountain.
I learned about this from a graduate student here at Carnegie Mellon back in the 90s who developed this
notion, Tom Stricker.
And what it is, it's a, the memory mountain, plots a measure called read throughput, or read bandwidth,
which is the number of bytes read from memory.
So if you have a loop and you're scanning over a vector, you're scanning over a vector,
So you have a vector of, say, say, double words,
and you're reading those elements from a vector, one after the other.
The read throughput is the number of megabytes per second that you can,
that you can perform that task at.
And the memory mountain plots read throughput as a function of the temporal and spatial locality
in that loop.
Okay, so in a sense, it's looking at a wide range of locality options or characteristics in
program and it's plotting the performance of that memory system on that across that range as a two-dimensional function.
So in some ways the memory mountain is a kind of a fingerprint, right? Every system has its own unique memory
mountain that we can measure, right, by writing a simple program. And so the idea here is that to
construct the memory mountain, we write a program called test. And for some reason it's not, okay.
All right. So when we build a memory mountain, we're given a vector that consists of a collection of a collection of double words. And then we write a loop that reads those words that reads some number of words. In this case, there we go. So it reads, it reads Elems number of elements, right? So we've got each of these double word elements, with a stride of
stride.
Okay, so if we have a stride of one, I know that was kind of redundant, huh?
So if we have a stride of one, then we'll, we'll have our loop, we'll sort of loop through and read these
elements until we've read elements, number of those elements. Okay? And then we'll do it again, and then that
warms up the cache. Then we do it again and do exactly the same thing. So if we're doing
this with a stride of 2, then we would be reading, we would read this word 0,
or LM2, LM4, and so on. Okay. So what all we're doing, we're just for wide range of strides
and a wide range of sizes, we're scanning over this vector and just recording how long it takes
to do that read. And then convert, we convert that into megabytes per second.
And in order to, I just wanted to show you this, this is, we don't need, we're not going to go into detail about this, but this is actually how I generated the cover on the book.
And in order to, in order to use, to exploit the parallelism inside the Intel processor, you know, like you learned about last week, there's a lot of parallel functional units, in order to exploit those, I, I, I did four by four loop unrolling, so I'm actually doing sort of
four scans in parallel. But the general idea is just what I've showed you here.
And this this four by four, this four, this four-by-four loop unrolling is just an optimization.
But I wanted to show it to you because it actually, it's, it's the exact same principles you learned about
last week when Professor Bryant talked about code optimization. So what we do is we call this
test function with these, these various ranges of elements and stride. And then we measure
the performance and we get this beautiful picture, this beautiful function.
To me it's beautiful, I don't know. Does it look beautiful to you?
So on the Z, our Z axis is plotting read throughput in megabytes per second, ranging from
2,000 megabytes per second up to 16,000 megabytes per second. This axis. This axis is measuring
is stride. So going from stride 1 up to stride 12. And this axis is, so as we
as we increase stride, we're decreasing the spatial locality. All right? And this axis is the size axis. So
We're going from, I think, 16K up to 128 megabytes. So this is the number of
we're going to read each pass through.
So as we increase the size, we're sort of decreasing the impact of temporal locality because
we're, as we increase the size, there's fewer and fewer and fewer caches in our hierarchy can
hold all that data.
And so this, so we've got spatial locality decreasing in this direction and temporal locality decreasing
in this direction.
So as a programmer,
what you want to do, you want to be up here, right? Good spatial locality, good temporal locality, because you can get like 14 gigabytes per second measured read throughput.
You don't want to be down here, which is only about 100 megabytes per second, where you're reading out of memory.
Right? So the difference between reading all of your data from memory and or reading it from some part of the caches is huge.
It's enormous.
So because you're 213 students, you'll be up here and all the students that didn't take 213, they'll be down here.
And I've actually had, I've actually had people, several people, right back to tell me about their experiences, you know, in internships and jobs after they left CMU,
where they were given some code that that was down here, and they recognized the locality issues and they got it, you know, better up here, or close, at least better.
So this.
This picture, this so-called memory mountain, has all kinds of interesting features.
First of all, there's these what I call ridges of temporal locality, where these ridges, you see these ridge lines?
If you think of this as like a mountain.
You see this ridge line, and you see this ridge line, and here's another ridge line, and then here's another one.
These correspond to different levels in the hierarchy.
So this top ridge line is where you're reading directly out of L1.
And it should be perfectly flat.
It's so fast that we're getting like measurement jitter, performance jitter, right?
But it's, it's, and this little drop-off here is a measurement artifact.
It shouldn't be there. It should be, it should be flat and go all the way to the wall back here.
And then here, this ridge line is where we're accessing L2.
This is where we're accessing L3, and here's where we're accessing L3, and here's where we're accessing mostly from memory.
So you have these ridges of temporal locality, and then you have these slopes of decreasing spatial locality.
So you see the slope here?
As we're, so as we're moving from the top of this slope down to the bottom, we're decreasing our spatial locality,
so we're getting less benefit for these blocks that we're bringing in.
So you can see the, we're getting less benefit out of the cost that we went through of importing, of fetching these blocks.
blocks. And once the stride hits the block size, now every reference is hitting a different block, and so then it
it flattens out. Then you're getting no benefit from spatial locality. And similarly, similarly, here is where this slope is where we're reading from L3, and it
it flattened out. They always flattened out at the, at the block size, which is a stride. These
These are double words, right? So it's stride of eight is 64 bytes.
So once you exceed a stride of eight, then you're no longer, you're missing every time in a different block.
And there's this interesting, this one puzzled me for a while.
You might be wondering, like, how come, like, over here, as we increase the size, we can sort of, we're sort of getting the, we're sort of getting the, we're sort of, as we increase the size, we're sort of, we're doing most of our references out of caches that are lower in the cash hierarchy.
Okay. But except when we're doing stride one references, you can see all the way up to, to right at the
And right before it exceeds the size of L3, it's flat.
And it's running at the L2 rate, right?
So here's the L1 rate, and then it drops off.
And then it's running at a constant L2 rate until the data no longer fits in L3.
So I think what's going on here is that the hardware, the L2 cash hardware is recognizing, or maybe it's
an L1, but some, some logic in the cache system is recognizing the stride 1 reference
reference pattern, right? Because it sees all the addresses. It's, it's recognizing that stride
one pattern, and then it's aggressively pre-fetching from L3 into L2 so that those, so it's fetching
ahead of time. It's anticipating. It's saying, look, I've gotten five stride-one references in a row.
I'm going to go grab a whole bunch of blocks and load them all up because
by the principle of spatial locality, those blocks are going to be referenced in the near future.
So this was really neat, and this only happened within the last couple years.
So the Intel engineers are always hard at work.
And maybe by the time we do the next edition of the memory mountain, those systems will recognize stride 2
and, you know, other stride patterns too. But from this data, it appears,
that it's only recognizing stride one.
Okay, so you can,
we can improve the spatial and temporal locality of our programs
in several different ways.
One way to improve the spatial locality is to rearrange loops.
And I'll use matrix multiplication as an example.
So here's a sort of a simple matrix multiplication
code where we're multiplying
A times B and adding it, we're taking what's in of the IJth element of C, and then to that we're adding to that we're adding the sum, the inner product of row I of A and the row J of a column J of B.
Okay, and then so we're going through and for each IJ in this matrix C, we're computing an inner product and then creating that sum.
So we can actually, it turns out there's a lot of different ways to do matrix multiply.
And this is, we can permute these loops in any of six different possible permutations.
So this is a permutation where it's I followed by J followed by K, but five other possibilities are feasible.
And so we can actually analyze those, those different permutations, and predict which one will have the best performance.
Okay. So what we'll do is we'll look at the inner loop and we'll look at the
the access pattern of the inner loops and it's in the the access pattern on arrays C, A, and B.
Okay. So let's look at the IJK implementation that I just showed you. So as always, we focus on the
inner loop. And if you notice, this inner loop is doing a row-wise access of column A, and a column
access, I'm sorry, a row-wise access of array A and column-wise access of a row B.
So row-wise of A, column-wise of a column-wise of B. We don't really care about C because it's out, it's not in the inner loop.
Okay, so just ignore that. So given our assumption that we can hold, in this case, we're assuming that we can hold four of these integer elements in one block.
So the row-wise access, which has good spatial locality, will miss one every four accesses.
Okay, the very first reference will miss, and then the next three will hit.
And then the next reference after that will hit a new block.
Okay, so one out of four references to A will miss.
But because the access pattern for B is column-wise, every reference to B will miss.
Okay, so the average number of misses per loop iteration is 1.25.
1.25. Okay, the J-IK version is exactly the same pattern. K-I-J is a little different. Here, we're doing row-wise access of B and a row-wise access of C. So that's good, right? So now we've got stride 1 accesses on both B and C, and the reference to A is outside of the loop, so we don't care about it. So both B and C will miss one quarter of the time. Okay, so the total average number
misses per loop iteration will be 0.5.
That's pretty good.
And IKJ has the same, similar behavior.
Now, J.I is sort of the exact opposite.
J.K.I.
Does column-wise access of A
and column-wise access of C.
So right, we know that's a stinker, right?
And we, qualitatively know it's bad.
And we can compute that it'll miss one time per loop iteration.
So that'll be two, total of two misses.
per iteration and KJI has the same bad pattern.
Okay, so if we look at all these permutations, you can see that IJK and JIC miss 1.25 have 1.25 misses.
K.I.J. has 0.5 misses. And J.K.I. has 2 misses. So clearly, it looks like KI.J
and its brethren are the best option. The only difference is that KIJ has this additional store, so there might be a question.
Is that going to create, is that going to slow things down? Well, it turns out in systems, in storage systems,
rights are much easier to deal with than reads. Can you think about why that might be true?
So rights, you have a lot more flexibility than you do with reads. I mean, yes. That's exactly, yeah. So you can, you have options. You can do, you can write back, defer, you can defer writing
until the value, the value that you're written is actually used.
But when you read an item, you're stuck. You can't do anything until you get that data.
So it turns out that rights don't really, that this additional store doesn't really hurt us.
And so when we measure these on a modern system, you can see that the K-I-J, which has the fewest number of misses,
has, you see, we're getting like one miss, what we're plotting here is cycles per interloop iteration.
So each iteration is taking about one cycle, which is really good.
This IJK pattern, which was kind of the intermediate, 1.2 misses, that's sort of in between.
And the jkI, which has two misses per iteration, is the worst.
Okay, so what's interesting is we could actually, just by doing a little bit of analysis, simple analysis,
we could actually predict what this graph would look like.
Okay, and the last ten minutes of the class,
we're going to look at how to improve temporal locality.
Now, so what we did with, when we rearranged our loops in the matrix multiplication, what we
were doing was improving our spatial locality, right? But we didn't, we didn't
really do anything to improve the temporal locality. To improve temporal locality, you have to
use a technique called blocking. And this is important to understand because you're
going to need it in your cache lab, for one thing. But it's also a very general technique
any time you're having issues with temporal locality.
Okay, so we're not going to go into too much detail of this code, but what I did, I rewrote the matrix multiply
so that it operates, you know, a two-dimensional matrix that you can really just think of it as a
contiguous array of bytes.
So I just rewrote this code to operate on a contiguous array, a one-dimensional array.
And then I'm doing the indexing explicitly here.
So here, C, I times n plus j.
This is an end-by-end matrix. What I'm doing is I'm accessing the, I'm computing where the Ith row starts, and then I'm going to the j-th column of that row and then accessing that row and then accessing that element.
All right, so let's, but it's the same idea as before. So let's look at the misrate for this.
This is just our original, this is our original unblocked matrix multiply.
So what we're doing is we're computing
And we're doing that by taking an inner product of row zero and column zero.
Whoops.
So if you look at the, we're assuming that the cache, the cache blocks hold eight doubles and that the matrix
elements are doubles, then we're going to miss one eighth of the time.
Okay, so in the first iteration, we're going to miss, the first iteration does n of these things.
And since we're missing n over eight of the time, we're going to miss, the first iteration does n over eight of
we're missing one block for every eight references.
For each, for the first iteration, we're going to miss N over 8, and since there's n for each element,
for each block, I'm sorry. And then, oh, so this is the number of blocks and the number of
misses, and then we have n elements. So that the total number of misses is 9 over n divided by 8 misses
first iteration.
Okay.
The second iteration will have the same number of misses because of our assumptions about the size of this array.
So these rows are way too big to fit in the cache, so we never get any, we don't get any temporal locality.
Okay, so the total number of misses is 9N over 8 times the number of elements that we're updating,
which is n squared. Okay, so our total misses is 9 over 8 times n cubed.
now let's rewrite the code to use blocking and so you can look at this
code later but it's it's much simpler just to just to look at it pictorially so
what what we're doing instead of updating one element at a time we're updating a
subblock a b by b subblock and we're doing that just totally analogously to
when our original case were b equal one this this b by b
subblock in C is computed by taking an inner product of the subblocks of a
set of subblocks in a with a set of subblocks in a with a set of subblocks in B. And for each one of those
we're doing a little mini matrix multiplication. So we're taking this subblock
times this subblock plus the second subblock of A times the second subblock of A times the second subblock
of B plus the second subblock of B plus the third
subblock of a times the third subblock of B and so on.
Okay, so we're doing the same interproduct operation, but instead of on scalers, we're doing it
with these little, these little tiny matrices.
Okay. All right, so let's look at, let's look at what happens to the miss rate when
we do this. So there's, there's, there's n over B blocks in, in, in, in, in any, in any row,
or column. And since there's b squared, and there's b squared,
in each block, b times b, there's b squared over eight misses for each block.
Okay. And so then, and then since there's n over b blocks in each matrix and there's two matrices,
there's two n over b times b squared over eight misses for this first iteration. So that, that works out to be
to be nb divided by four. And the second iteration has the second iteration has the same, has a
the same miss, sort of same miss rate.
So the total number of misses is the number of the number of misses for each iteration times
times the number of elements in C that we're updating, okay, which is n over b squared.
So that all works out to, it's still n cubed divided by 4B.
So in our first case with no blocking, although that the number of misses is asymptotically, is
the same, but there's this pretty, this big difference in the constant factor.
So for no blocking, it's 9 over 8.
For blocking, it's 1 over 4B, where now we can just sort of drive that down by increasing the block size.
So this gives us some control.
But we still, we have, we can't make the block, the blocks too big because we need to fit
three blocks in cash at any one point in time.
Okay, so the reason, this is a dramatic difference, right?
And the reason for this is that by doing the blocking,
we're sort of exploiting, once we load a block into memory,
we're sort of reusing its items over and over again.
So we're exploiting more temporal locality.
And matrix multiplication has this implicit locality because the computation
is order n cubed, but the size of the data is n squared, right?
So we must be reusing some data items.
Right?
The problem with our
is that when we were reusing them, they weren't in the cache.
Okay.
All right.
So the point that I wanted to make with you is that cache memories, although they're sort of built-in automatic
hardware storage devices, and you can't really control them.
If you know about them, you can take advantage of your knowledge and exploit them and make your code
run faster. Okay. And the way you do this is, like I said, focus on the inner loops.
Do is try to do, try to do accesses that are stride 1, and try to maximize to maximize spatial locality,
and try to maximize temporal locality by reusing local variables, which can then be put into
registers. Okay, so that's it for today. Good luck with your attack lab if you haven't
finished it. And don't forget to get started on Cash Lab this weekend.
Thank you.